K. MICHAEL HAYS: The Maison Dom-ino would become an objet-type for Le Corbusier, an inaugural diagram that https://youtu.be/MSlexCUGpxk
K. MICHAEL HAYS: Ngôi nhà Dom-ino thực sự là một kiểu nhà điển hình (objet-type) đối với Le Corbusier, một tấm biểu đồ https://youtu.be/MSlexCUGpxk
would allow him to develop a number of houses in and around Paris.
cho phép ông xây dựng nên rất nhiều ngôi nhà ở trong và xung quanh thành phố Paris.
Looking at a few of the villas of Le Corbusier will allow us to further articulate the interaction
Một số biệt thự thiết kế bởi Le Corbusier sau đây sẽ giúp chúng ta liên hệ sâu hơn về sự tương tác
of new technology with the historical continuity of the discipline of architecture.
giữa nền kĩ thuật mới với sự tiếp diễn mang tính lịch sử của quy tắc về kiến trúc.
The first of these we'll look at is the Villa La Roche - Jeanneret.
Đầu tiên chúng ta sẽ quan sát ngôi nhà Villa La Roche của Jeanneret.
There was a planned development in a area of Paris that made the site very attractive
Có một sự phát triển đã được vạch sẵn ở một khu vực của Paris, điều này đã làm cho nơi đó trở nên hấp dẫn
because the plan was that a number of houses would be built on the same site.
vì theo kế hoạch, hàng loạt các ngôi nhà sẽ được xây ở cùng một địa điểm.
Le Corbusier was acting on behalf of the clients to negotiate an acquisition of a property,
Le Corbusier đã thay mặt khách hàng để thương lượng về sự sát nhập đất đai,
in which he could build two houses for two families-- kind of twins that would be bridged by a
từ đó ông có thể xây hai ngôi nhà cho hai gia đình-- kiểu nhà đôi được nối với nhau bởi
common gallery.
một hành lang thông thường.
In the end, he was not able to obtain the pair of lots he wanted that would make
Về sau, ông đã không thể đạt được thỏa thuận về đất đai để xây nên
a symmetrical entry.
một lối đi vào cân xứng.
So he ended up, rather than designing a U-shape scheme, he ended up with an L-shape, with
Do đó, thay vì thiết kế ngôi nhà theo hình chữ U, ông đã xây theo hình chữ L,
an extended wing on the right side of the street.
với một cánh được mở rộng về phía bên phải của con phố.
And what would have been the bridge, or what would have been this cross-wing, now became
Và thứ đã từng là cây cầu, hay chính là cái cánh bắc qua này, giờ đã trở thành
a gallery, raised up off the ground on columns, or what he called pilotis, and whose elevation
một phòng trưng bày, được nâng lên bởi các cột, hay ông gọi đó là bộ cọc nhà sàn, và sự nâng lên đó
he treated as a terminus of the cul-de-sac.
được ông thiết kế như điểm cuối của con ngõ cụt.
You approach the building toward this curved surface,
Bạn tiếp cận tòa nhà theo bề mặt cong này,
and then you turn 90 degrees to the right to enter the La Roche house into a three-story
và sau đó rẽ phải 90 độ sẽ đến căn nhà La Roche với hành lang có ba tầng,
hallway, a prism, that has an area nearly equal to all the other major living spaces
hình lăng trụ, có một khu vực gần như bằng với tất cả các không gian sống khác
combined.
gộp lại.
So visitors come in to this big entry hallway, then they mount a stairway at the far corner
Khách thăm quan sẽ đi vào tiền sảnh lớn này, sau đó leo lên cầu thang ở trong góc
of the hall.
của căn phòng.
Coming up the stairway, at the very top, is a balcony.
Phía trên cùng của cầu thang là một cái ban công.
And you're immediately, as you reach the top of the stair, you're oriented back to the
Và ngay khi bạn lên đến đỉnh cầu thang, bạn sẽ được dẫn trở lại với
space of the entry hall, to the open space of the entry hall, from where you have just
không gian của sảnh vào, đến với không gian mở của tiền sảnh, nơi mà bạn vừa mới
come, as well as to other apertures, windows, and passages that punctuate through the walls
vào, cũng như đến những hốc tường, cửa sổ, và lối đi xuyên qua các bức tường
of the entry hall.
của tiền sảnh.
From there, you can choose a number of different paths that take you to further moments
Từ đó, bạn có thể chọn đi nhiều lối khác nhau có thể mang đến cho bạn những khoảnh khắc
of stasis.
của sự ngưng trệ.
You come to the top of the stair, you pause.
Bạn đi lên đỉnh cầu thang, sau đó dừng lại.
You move along a different path, and you pause again, either at a balcony, or an aperture,
Bạn đi theo một lối khác, và bạn dừng lại lần nữa, sẽ đến một ban công, hoặc một hốc tường,
or in a window.
hay một cái cửa sổ.
You can also move into the main gallery, with its curved front, which is on the primary
Bạn có thể di chuyển tới phòng trưng bày chính có dạng cong ở phần trước, ở tầng một--
floor-- that is, the first floor above the ground, since it's been raised on pilotis.
đó chính là tầng đầu phía trên mặt đất, bởi nó được nâng lên bởi bộ cọc.
Now, this gallery was intended for the display of paintings that had been collected by
Hiện giờ, căn phòng này được chỉ định cho việc trưng bày các bức họa sưu tầm bởi
La Roche, the owner.
La Roche, chủ ngôi nhà.
It's a two-story space, as I say, raised one story off the ground.
Đó là một không gian hai tầng, như tôi đã nói, tầng thứ nhất được nâng cao hơn so với mặt đất.
On the main floor, there's a ramp rising slowly along the curve of the gallery's long wall.
Ở chỗ sàn chính là một đoạn tường dốc thoải được nâng lên dọc theo đường cong của bức tường.
This is the same wall that is the elevation of the entry court.
Đoạn này giống với bức tường được nâng lên ở chỗ sảnh ra vào.
At the bottom of that ramp is another balcony that, this time, punches through the exterior
Ở cuối đoạn tường dốc là một cái ban công khác, nhưng lần này, nó đâm xuyên qua
wall to take you to the outside.
bức tường chắn, giúp bạn có thể nhìn ra bên ngoài.
From that balcony, you can survey the whole project-- the elevation that would be to your
Từ ban công này, bạn có thể nhìn tổng thể dự án-- phần được nâng lên ở bên trái của bạn,
left, as well as the curved wall, as well as the entry court itself.
cũng như bức tường cong, và cả sân vào nữa.
Now, walking up the ramp, we get a cinematic experience of the gallery.
Bây giờ, đi lên dốc, chúng ta sẽ có một trải nghiệm như trong phim khi tham quan phòng trưng bày.
It's like one long, uninterrupted shot of the abstract geometry and structure
Kết cấu và hình dạng của căn phòng đã làm cho không gian như
of that space.
trải dài và liên tục.
And then, finally, when we reach the top of that, yet another balcony flanked by two long,
Cuối cùng, khi lên tới đỉnh dốc, chúng ta sẽ thấy một ban công nữa ở giữa
horizontal windows that afford a view out on both sides, now, of the building.
hai cửa sổ dài nằm ngang mà từ đó, bạn có thể ngắm cảnh cả hai phía của tòa nhà.
Every view of the geometry and the compositional features of the house must be taken in as
Mỗi góc nhìn về hình khối và những đặc điểm cấu tạo của ngôi nhà phải được hiểu
a result of movement, of movement through the spaces and movement through walls, through
theo sự vận động qua các không gian và sự dịch chuyển qua các bức tường, qua
surfaces, and around figures and walls.
bề mặt, và vòng quanh các bức tường.
The motion is choreographed with extreme care in a narrative of pure form.
Sự vận động ấy được dàn dựng với sự quan tâm kỹ lưỡng dưới dạng nguyên bản.
The house is perceived as a geometrical construction by walking through and around the main space
Ngôi nhà được hiểu là một phép dựng hình bằng cách đi xuyên qua và vòng quanh không gian chính
in a process of rotation through the space.
trong quy trình quay vòng của không gian.
Then there are moments of pause in this movement that are usually designated, either by a balcony
Tiếp đó có những chỗ ngắt quãng của sự vận động này, thường được tạo ra bởi một cái ban công
at a handrail, at which you come to rest, or perhaps by an aperture or a window, where
ở chỗ lan can, nơi bạn dừng chân để nghỉ ngơi, hoặc có thể là một hốc tường hay cửa sổ, nơi
you come and register your body and measure it in that aperture that creates these moments
mà bạn đến và thả lỏng cơ thể, đó là những vị trí góp phần tạo ra những khoảnh khắc
of stasis.
của sự tĩnh tại.
At these moments of stasis, one looks across the space, usually at walls or other surfaces,
Tại những khoảnh khắc này, bạn nhìn từ bên này sang bên kia, thường sẽ nhìn vào các bức tường hay những bề mặt khác,
in a frontal way.
theo hướng trước mặt.
So the moments of stasis establish a perception of frontality.
Vì thế, những khoảnh khắc ngưng đọng này đã tạo nên ý niệm về hình vẽ điêu khắc theo mặt trước.
This dialectic of rotation and frontality, or movement and stasis, is one of the themes
Mối biện chứng giữa sự quay vòng và thiết kế theo mặt trước, hay sự dịch chuyển và tĩnh tại, là một trong những đề tài
that is definitive for the villas.
chính thức để xây các căn biệt thự.
Now, there are two kinds of what we might even think of as knowledge or as information
Hiện giờ có hai thứ mà chúng ta hay nghĩ đó là kiến thức hay thông tin
that's produced by this dialectic.
được đưa ra bởi sự biện chứng này.
Frontality is normally perceived at a distance, at a prospect.
Hình vẽ điêu khắc theo mặt trước thường được nhìn từ một khoảng cách hay từ viễn cảnh.
It might be something that you scan, but usually you're looking at it in a kind of perspective
Nó có thể là một thứ gì đó mà bạn nhìn lướt qua, nhưng thường bạn sẽ nhìn ở khía cạnh
that produces pictorial space.
cho thấy cả không gian tranh ảnh.
Now, pictorial space is a space that is very like that in Le Corbusier's painting, is space
Đến đây, không gian tranh ảnh là không gian rất giống với những gì Le Corbusier thể hiện trong các bức họa của mình,
that cannot be entered or circulated through.
đó là không gian không thể được nhìn xuyên qua.
It's rather viewed from a distance, assigned a frontality, and it gives order to that frontal
Mà nó phải được nhìn chính diện từ một khoảng cách, điều này đưa ra trật tự về cảm giác
sensation.
ở đằng trước.
Now, against this, Corbusier stages a different kind of experience.
Now, against this, Corbusier stages a different kind of experience.
And it produces a different kind of knowledge, or a different kind of information, that one
And it produces a different kind of knowledge, or a different kind of information, that one
can only have by being close up to things, close to the wall, close to the aperture,
can only have by being close up to things, close to the wall, close to the aperture,
at the sill of the window, at the handrail of the balcony.
at the sill of the window, at the handrail of the balcony.
So it's close up,
So it's close up,
and it requires movement and rotation through and around space.
and it requires movement and rotation through and around space.
So again, the dialectic of frontality and rotation combine to produce a kind of spatial
So again, the dialectic of frontality and rotation combine to produce a kind of spatial
and formal knowledge, combine to produce architectural information in the architectural imaginary,
and formal knowledge, combine to produce architectural information in the architectural imaginary,
combine to produce a concept of the architecture.
combine to produce a concept of the architecture.
Well, at Villa La Roche, Le Corbusier was able to explore some of the properties of
Well, at Villa La Roche, Le Corbusier was able to explore some of the properties of
the Dom-ino diagram, like the use of the reinforced concrete system, the horizontal slabs, which
the Dom-ino diagram, like the use of the reinforced concrete system, the horizontal slabs, which
allow the free arrangement of program and circulation, the non-load-bearing wall, the
allow the free arrangement of program and circulation, the non-load-bearing wall, the
relationship of the earth, where he explored raising some of the rooms on pilotis.
relationship of the earth, where he explored raising some of the rooms on pilotis.
He wasn't able to fully explore all of the Dom-ino system.
He wasn't able to fully explore all of the Dom-ino system.
What he found, however, in addition to that, was a way of supplementing the system with
What he found, however, in addition to that, was a way of supplementing the system with
a kind of formal vocabulary for architecture.
a kind of formal vocabulary for architecture.
He discovered that the objet-type in his paintings-- the bottles, the plates, the contours of the
He discovered that the objet-type in his paintings-- the bottles, the plates, the contours of the
guitar, the everyday objects that he thought provided such an effect and such deep sensation
guitar, the everyday objects that he thought provided such an effect and such deep sensation
when experienced visually-- he made analogs of those objet-type in the architecture.
when experienced visually-- he made analogs of those objet-type in the architecture.
The balconies, the apertures, the curvilinear surfaces-- these became an architectural vocabulary
The balconies, the apertures, the curvilinear surfaces-- these became an architectural vocabulary
that was analogous to the objet-type in the paintings and supplemented the objet-type of
that was analogous to the objet-type in the paintings and supplemented the objet-type of
the Dom-ino system itself.
the Dom-ino system itself.